<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-03-29T09:12:33+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leiden HumAN</title><subtitle>Combining forces of the humanities and Artificial Intelligence</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Dialectometry</title><link href="/2024/02/07/intro-to-dialectometry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Dialectometry" /><published>2024-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2024/02/07/intro-to-dialectometry</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/02/07/intro-to-dialectometry.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/ITD.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<h1 id="introduction-to-dialectometry-2024">Introduction to Dialectometry (2024)</h1>

<p>Many proposals of dialect classification use isoglosses to identify dialect areas. However, isogloss maps are often messy, and they are also susceptible to some further problems: 
1) features shown on a map can potentially be cherry-picked; 
2) very often it is difficult to analyse many features all at once, 
3) it is difficult to analyse the relationship between dialects (areas) which are geographically distant and 
4) it is difficult to assess how representative features are in an analysis.</p>

<p>In order to overcome these problems and make dialect classifications more objective, dialectologists have employed computational methods in dialectology, often known as  <em>dialectometry</em> , the measurement of dialect distances. Dialectometry applies a set of techniques on a large amount of dialect data in order to get an aggregate picture of the variation hidden the dialect landscape.</p>

<p>In this workshop series, the reasoning behind the dialectometric approaches will first be introduced in the first week, then in the following weeks, various techniques in dialectometry will be introduced with hands on exercises. Lastly, the workshop series will end with an overview of the contemporary approaches in the field.</p>

<p>Programming knowledge is not required for this workshop series.</p>

<h1 id="time--location">Time &amp; Location</h1>

<p>Tuesdays: 27 February; 12 March; 26 March; 9 April; 23 April at PJ Veth 1.07 DH Lab</p>

<h3 id="availability">Availability</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.formdesk.com/universiteitleiden/intro_dialectometry_2024">Registration</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Matthew Sung</name></author><category term="Workshop" /><category term="Dialectometry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Learning for the Humanities Workshop</title><link href="/2024/02/06/deep-learning-for-beginners-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Learning for the Humanities Workshop" /><published>2024-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2024/02/06/deep-learning-for-beginners-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/02/06/deep-learning-for-beginners-2024.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="deep-learning-for-the-humanities-workshop">Deep Learning for the Humanities workshop</h1>

<p>Deep-learning has been used in many recent applications You’ve likely seen use cases such as Stable diffusion - image generation, ChatGPT text generation, image classification and, object detection in self-driving cars. Deep-learning is also gaining popularity in the humanities, even beyond NLP uses.</p>

<p>In this workshop we are teaching humanities students &amp; researchers how to train neural networks using PyTorch, thereby allowing them to eventually use this for their own research interests. Meaning this course is heavily focused onto the practical side of neural network programming.</p>

<p>The main focus revolves around visual data, but the basics taught in this course are equally important for language or audio related deep learning:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Session</th>
      <th>Date</th>
      <th>Topic</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Session 1</td>
      <td>6 February</td>
      <td>Tensors</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session 2</td>
      <td>20 February</td>
      <td>Linear regression (Training Pt 1.)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session 2</td>
      <td>5 March</td>
      <td>Non-Linear Data (Training Pt 2. &amp; Evaluation)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session 3</td>
      <td>19 March</td>
      <td>Images as Data</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session 4</td>
      <td>2 April</td>
      <td>Image classification</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session 5</td>
      <td>16 April</td>
      <td>Transfer Learning</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session 6</td>
      <td>30 April</td>
      <td>Spill-over Session</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="https://www.dlfh.aronvandepol.com/">More Information</a></p>

<h3 id="location">Location</h3>

<p>Digital Lab, P.J. Veth 1.07 Time: biweekly starting 6th of Feb. 13-15</p>

<h3 id="availability">Availability</h3>]]></content><author><name>Aron van de Pol</name></author><category term="Workshop" /><category term="Deep learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Deep Learning for the Humanities workshop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leiden HumAN researchers talk at Oxford Internet Institute</title><link href="/2024/01/31/oii-indonesia-talk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leiden HumAN researchers talk at Oxford Internet Institute" /><published>2024-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2024/01/31/oii-indonesia-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/31/oii-indonesia-talk.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="zooming-in-on-the-digital-aspects-of-the-indonesian-election">Zooming in on the digital aspects of the Indonesian election</h1>

<p>Leiden HumAN researchers Wang Ngai Yeung and Leiden Institute for Area Studies researcher Dr. Rizal Shidiq will present at the upcoming event at the Oxford Internet Institute (OII) on their latest work Political Social Network in Indonesia (POLISONI).</p>

<h3 id="about-the-event">About the event</h3>

<p>2024 is already promising to be an important year for elections, as over 40% of the world’s population will be eligible to vote. Digital technologies can impact campaigns, political participation, and elections in many ways. In the first event of the OII elections initiative, we would like to zoom in on the digital aspects of the Indonesian election.  We will introduce the background of the Indonesian election and its importance and cover how digital media and technologies are being used by political actors. Additionally, we will discuss online content governance in the context of tensions and power negotiations involved in moderating political content. Relying on social data science approaches, we will present a database on Indonesian candidate profiles developed by researchers at Leiden University. Please join us for a discussion of the different digital aspects of the Indonesian election.</p>

<h3 id="location">Location</h3>
<p>In-person (1 St Giles, Oxford) / Online</p>

<h3 id="date--time">Date &amp; Time</h3>
<p>Wednesday 7 Feb 2024, 18:00 - 19:00 (CEST)</p>

<h3 id="registration">Registration</h3>
<p>Click <a href="https://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/news-events/events/zooming-in-on-the-digital-aspects-of-the-indonesian-election/">here</a> to register</p>]]></content><author><name>Admin</name></author><category term="Talk" /><category term="Leiden HumAN" /><category term="Oxford Internet Institute" /><category term="Indonesia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Zooming in on the digital aspects of the Indonesian election]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Political Social Networks in Indonesia 15 Dec 2023</title><link href="/2023/12/12/POLISONI-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Political Social Networks in Indonesia 15 Dec 2023" /><published>2023-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2023/12/12/POLISONI-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/12/POLISONI-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="polisoni-project-is-organizing-a-workshop-on-15-december">PoliSoNI project is organizing a workshop on 15 December</h1>

<p>Political social networks in Indonesia is a multidisciplinary project aiming at creating a large-scale digital database of the profiles of aspiring politicians for the upcoming 2024 general elections in Indonesia. On 14 February 2024 Indonesia, home of 205 million registered eligible voters, will hold a massive-scale general election, with about 300,000 candidates running for 20,614 political seats. Political social networks in Indonesia project combines expertise in political economy of Indonesia (LIAS/SSEA) and expertise in web scraping, social network analysis and machine learning (LUCDH/LUCL), in order to make election data freely and easily accessible to all researchers interested in the political economy and democracy in Indonesia.</p>

<p>In this workshop we will present the preliminary results of the project and discuss it with both experts in Indonesian general elections/politics and software developers. The workshop is open to everyone interested in Indonesian 2024 elections and how digital technologies can help us in using web data to create easily accessible research materials for studies on politics and political economy.</p>

<h3 id="organizers">Organizers</h3>
<p>Jelena Prokic &amp; Rizal Shidiq</p>

<h3 id="location">Location</h3>
<p>Location: Digital Lab, P.J. Veth 1.07</p>

<h3 id="date--time">Date &amp; Time</h3>
<p>15 December 2023; 10:00-12:00</p>]]></content><author><name>Admin</name></author><category term="Workshop" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[PoliSoNI project is organizing a workshop on 15 December]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SAILS Workshop - December 2023</title><link href="/2023/12/06/SAILS-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SAILS Workshop - December 2023" /><published>2023-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2023/12/06/SAILS-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/06/SAILS-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="sails-workshop-ai-and-llms-keeping-the-linguist-in-the-loop">SAILS workshop “AI and LLMs: Keeping the Linguist in the Loop”</h1>

<p>On Friday, 8 December, Jelena Prokic will will take part in the discussion panel at the SAILS workshop titled “AI and LLMs: Keeping the Linguist in the Loop” at Leiden University. Panel discussion with Sjef Barbiers and Vincent Vandeghinste, moderated by Carole Tiberius.</p>]]></content><author><name>Admin</name></author><category term="LLMs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[SAILS workshop “AI and LLMs: Keeping the Linguist in the Loop”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Clariah LLM Talk</title><link href="/2023/11/30/clariah.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clariah LLM Talk" /><published>2023-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2023/11/30/clariah</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/30/clariah.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="navigating-chatgpt-a-primer-on-functionality-safety-and-academic-use">Navigating ChatGPT: A Primer on Functionality, safety and Academic Use</h1>

<p><img src="/resources/primer.png" alt="" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p>Aron’s presentation at the CLARIAH Annual Conference 2023, “Navigating ChatGPT: A Primer on Functionality, Safety, and Academic Use,” offered a succinct exploration into the workings of ChatGPT and large language models (LLMs). He explained their mechanisms, touched on the significance of open-source models for academia, and provided examples of their academic applications. Aron also delved into critical issues like LLM jailbreaking and security, emphasizing the need for ethical usage and robust safeguards in academic research. This talk was a valuable primer for anyone looking to understand or apply ChatGPT and LLMs in their work.</p>]]></content><author><name>Aron van de Pol</name></author><category term="Talks" /><category term="LLM" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Navigating ChatGPT: A Primer on Functionality, safety and Academic Use]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcoming new member - Ada Shi November 2023</title><link href="/2023/11/23/new-member-ada.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcoming new member - Ada Shi November 2023" /><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2023/11/23/new-member-ada</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/23/new-member-ada.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="leiden-human-welcomes-its-new-student-researcher-ada-shi">Leiden HumAN welcomes its new student researcher Ada Shi</h1>

<p>Ada Shi has joined HumAN lab in November 2023. She is a third-year Bachelor’s Communication
Science student at the University of Amsterdam. Ada will work as a research assistant in the
Digital warfare in the Sahel project, where she will focus on the usage of social
media in the Sahel region.</p>]]></content><author><name>Admin</name></author><category term="New member" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Leiden HumAN welcomes its new student researcher Ada Shi]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Applications of Large Language Models to the Humanities Workshop 21 Nov 2023</title><link href="/2023/11/05/llms-humanities-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applications of Large Language Models to the Humanities Workshop 21 Nov 2023" /><published>2023-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2023/11/05/llms-humanities-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/05/llms-humanities-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="applications-of-large-language-models-to-the-humanities-workshop">Applications of Large Language Models to the Humanities Workshop</h1>

<p>In this workshop, we will explore different approaches for applying a Large Language Model (like BERT) to a specific tagging problem in the context of Computational Humanities research. Following up on the current “pre-train and fine-tune” paradigm in the field of Computational Linguistics, we will try to reach an understanding of the techniques used in the “fine-tuning” step. Besides this theoretical part, we will have a hands-on session on working with computing clusters. Because carrying out this type of approach requires computational power often not available in personal computers, we will walk through an example of how to script and deploy fine-tuning jobs on ALICE (the high performance computing cluster at Leiden University). We will complete the workshop emphasising the need for evaluation and comparison of different approaches before consuming the output of the fine-tuned models.</p>

<h3 id="instructor">Instructor</h3>
<p>Enrique Manjavacas Arevalo</p>

<h3 id="location">Location</h3>
<p>Location: Digital Lab, P.J. Veth 1.07</p>

<h3 id="date--time">Date &amp; Time</h3>
<p>The workshop will take place on 21 Nov 2023, 10:00-13:00</p>

<h3 id="availability">Availability</h3>
<p>This workshop is only available in person. Please register <a href="https://fd24.formdesk.com/universiteitleiden/LLM-Workshop-21nov2023">here</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Admin</name></author><category term="Workshop" /><category term="LLMs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Applications of Large Language Models to the Humanities Workshop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Workshop on Methods in Dialectology Oct 2023 - Nov 2023</title><link href="/2023/09/13/computational-dialectology-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workshop on Methods in Dialectology Oct 2023 - Nov 2023" /><published>2023-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2023/09/13/computational-dialectology-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/09/13/computational-dialectology-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="new-workshop-on-the-latest-methods-in-dialectology">New workshop on the latest methods in dialectology</h1>

<p>Interested in dialects? Want to know how to analyse dialects? Want to learn how to create linguistic maps? Then this is the workshop for you! This semester, the Leiden Dialectology Workshop Series will give 5 workshops on different aspects of dialectology; you will learn how to read maps, extract dialect data as well as creating your own linguistic maps with hands on experience.</p>

<p>Dialectology, the study of language variation across geographical space, may not be a subject that is as accessible to everyone as before. At the end of the 19th century and throughout the 20th century, there were numerous dialect surveys conducted around the world, and some of these surveys were published as linguistic atlases (maps) and dialect surveys (tables, lists). These data typically reflect the more old-fashioned speech spoken in rural areas, which were on the verge of extinction when the surveys were conducted due to societal changes. These data, now mostly sitting in the library in book form, are covered in dust and are waiting for more people to utilize them. This workshop series aims to introduce the kind of data present in these linguistic atlases/ dialect surveys, as well as to introduce how to extract these data and analyze them.</p>

<p>Throughout the semester, we will digitize a dialect dataset together. From this process, we can learn what kind of problems one might face in digitization, as well as learning how to overcome some of them. The digitized dataset will be used in the next semester (Introduction to Dialectometry 2024).</p>

<p>Please find the syllabus of the workshop <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/13QNSMlWtftnXc_oGkL4SP9w0h9zo_pUP/view">here</a></p>

<h3 id="instructor">Instructor</h3>
<p>Matthew Sung</p>

<h3 id="location">Location</h3>
<p>Location: Digital Lab, P.J. Veth 1.07</p>

<h3 id="date--time">Date &amp; Time</h3>
<p>The workshop will run from Oct 2023 - Nov 2023</p>

<h3 id="availability">Availability</h3>
<p>This workshop is only available in person. Please register <a href="https://fd24.formdesk.com/universiteitleiden/form692543424">here</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Admin</name></author><category term="Workshop" /><category term="Dialectology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[New workshop on the latest methods in dialectology]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Learning for Beginners Feb 2024 - Apr 2024</title><link href="/2023/09/13/deep-learning-for-beginners-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Learning for Beginners Feb 2024 - Apr 2024" /><published>2023-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T09:10:31+00:00</updated><id>/2023/09/13/deep-learning-for-beginners-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/09/13/deep-learning-for-beginners-2024.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-to-make-a-computer-think-like-a-human">How to Make a Computer Think like a Human</h1>

<p>Deep-learning has been used in many recent applications. You’ve likely seen use cases such as Stable diffusion, DALL-E image generation, ChatGPT text generation, image classification and, object detection in self-driving cars. Deep-learning is also gaining popularity in the humanities beyond NLP uses. Here are the topics we will cover:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Tensors</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Single Linear Neuron Models and Training Loop</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Multi-Layer Models and Activation Functions</strong></li>
  <li><strong>(Images as Data: CNN and Data Loaders</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Evaluation Metrics and Model Performances</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Transfer Learning and Practical Applications&lt;/strong</strong></li>
</ol>

<p>Please find the syllabus of the workshop <a href="https://www.universiteitleiden.nl/binaries/content/assets/geesteswetenschappen/lucdh/events/deep_learning_for_beginners_2024-aron_vd_pol.pdf">here</a></p>

<p>Join our 6-part workshop series and go from zero to building a basic image classification model. With this knowledge, you can continue to teach yourself further in expanding beyond the focus of images onto other forms of data such a text (NLP tasks).</p>

<h3 id="instructor">Instructor</h3>
<p>Aron van de Pol</p>

<h3 id="location">Location</h3>
<p>Location: Digital Lab, P.J. Veth 1.07</p>

<h3 id="date--time">Date &amp; Time</h3>
<p>The workshop will run from Feb 2024 - Apr 2024</p>

<h3 id="availability">Availability</h3>
<p>This workshop is only available in person. Please register <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdk0NqAA0LrNxg5ObRC9IUajTH4HUPPiABgS5QBn6gJfY2oSg/viewform">here</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Admin</name></author><category term="Workshop" /><category term="Deep learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to Make a Computer Think like a Human]]></summary></entry></feed>